# JOSHUA S. SPEAGLE

Statistical Sciences, Astronomy & Astrophysics, Dunlap Institute University of Toronto

joshspeagle.github.io | j.speagle@utoronto.ca

### RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research interests lie in the interdisciplinary fields of **astrostatistics** and **data science** at the intersections of statistics, astronomy, and computer science. I develop methods and analyse large datasets to better understand how galaxies like our own **Milky Way** form, behave, and evolve.

### **POSITIONS**

Banting & Dunlap Postdoctoral Fellow: University of Toronto	2020-present
Joint between Statistical Sciences, Astronomy & Astrophysics, & the Dunlap Institute	
Supervisor: Gwen Eadie	
Project Academic Support Staff: Kavli IPMU, University of Tokyo	2015-2016
Supervisors: Naoki Yoshida, Alexie Leauthaud, & Kevin Bundy	

#### **EDUCATION**

Harvard University: PhD in Astronomy	2016-2020
Advisers: Doug Finkbeiner, Charlie Conroy, Daniel Eisenstein, & Alyssa Goodman	
Harvard University: MA in Astronomy	2016-2020
Advisers: Daniel Eisenstein & Alexie Leauthaud	
Harvard University: BA in Astrophysics and Physics	2011-2015

### **AWARDS & HONORS**

Best Astrostatistics Student Paper Award (ASA/AIG)	2020
Eric R. Keto Prize for Best Thesis in Theoretical Astrophysics (Harvard)	2020
Banting Postdoctoral Fellowship (Canada)	2020
Department of Astronomy Teaching Award (Harvard)	Spring 2018
Bok Center Certificate of Distinction in Teaching (Harvard)	Spring 2017, 18; Fall 2018
NSF Graduate Research Fellowship (USA)	2016

### **TEACHING**

I have a strong interest in education and pedagogy, with a focus on skills such as **programming**, **statistics**, **and data science**. See my <u>teaching statement</u> for additional details.

# **EQUITY, DIVERSITY, & INCLUSION**

I am committed to improving equity, diversity, and inclusion (EDI) in the classroom, in my work, and in the wider academic community. See my **EDI statement** for additional details.

### **STUDENTS**

Mingxuan Teng (4<sup>th</sup> year undergraduate, University of Toronto)

Zhiya Lou (4<sup>th</sup> year undergraduate, University of Toronto)

Co-supervised with Gwen Eadie

Alan Tu (2<sup>nd</sup> year undergraduate, Harvard)

Co-supervised with Catherine Zucker & Gus Beane

Summer 2020-Present

Kaustav Das (4<sup>th</sup> year undergraduate, IIT Kanpur)

Summer 2019-Fall 2020

Co-supervised with Catherine Zucker

### **PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES**

Web Director 2020-present

Astrostatistics Interest Group (American Statistical Association)

Steering Committee Member 2020-present

Working Group on Astroinformatics & Astrostatistics (American Astronomical Society)

Journal Clubs

Co-Founder: Statistics & Machine Learning Journal Club (University of Toronto)

Co-Organizer: astro-ph Coffee (University of Toronto)

Founder: Center for Astrophysics Machine Learning Journal Club (Harvard University)

2020-present
2020-present
2021-2020

Manuscript Referee

Journal of Open Source Software2020-presentAstronomy & Astrophysics2017-presentMonthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society2016-presentAmerican Astronomical Society Journals2014-present

## **SELECTED PRESENTATIONS**

# University of Florida: Colloquium

September 2020

Enabling Data-Driven Discovery in the Milky Way and Beyond Using Large Astronomical Datasets

### Astro Hack Week 2020: Tutorial Leader

August 2020

Introduction to Bayesian Inference with Linear Regression

# Villanova: Colloquium

October 2019

Exploring the Galaxy Near and Far in the Age of Gaia

# Harvard: Summer Colloquium (joint with Catherine Zucker)

June 2019

Charting Nearby Molecular Clouds with Gaia: A New Map of Our Local Interstellar Medium

### GitHub Satellite 2019: Keynote Address Participant

May 2019

Invited for open source code contributions (dynesty) in the analysis of the supermassive black hole in M87 by the Even Horizon Telescope collaboration

# University of Toronto: Special Seminar

April 2019

Photometric Distances Near and Far in the Age of Gaia

Max Planck Institute for Astronomy: Galaxy Coffee

The Devil's in the Detail's: Photometric Biases in Modern Surveys

Cambridge: Data Intensive Science Seminar

April 2019

April 2019

Mapping the 3-D Distribution of Dust in the Milky Way with Stellar Photometry

Harvard: CMSA Big Data Conference

August 2018

Revealing the Milky Way's Dust-iny

UMass Amherst: Data Science Tea

October 2017

Big Data Inference: Combining Hierarchical Bayes and Machine Learning to Improve Photometric Redshifts

Harvard: CHASC Astrostatistics Seminar

September 2017

An Introduction to Dynamic Nested Sampling

Kavli IPMU: Astronomy Lunch Seminar

March 2016

Mapping, Visualizing, and Exploiting the Color-Redshift Relation

University of Tsukuba: Theoretical Astrophysics Seminar

August 2013

The Evolution of Star-Forming Galaxies over Cosmic Time

### **PUBLICATIONS**

I am an author of **45 papers** that have over **2900 citations** (<u>h-index=17</u>). This includes:

10 papers as (co-)first author (in red) with over 1000 citations (h-index=7)

15 papers with substantial contributions (in blue) with over 600 citations (h-index=9)

Most of my papers can be found online on <u>arxiv</u> and <u>ADS</u>. My ORCID is <u>0000-0003-2573-9832</u>. Projects that have been led by students I have (co-)supervised are highlighted in <u>orange</u>.

# In Preparation

- **Tu, A. J.**; Zucker, C.; Beane, A.; **Speagle, J. S.**; Goodman, A.; Alves, J.; Faherty, J.; & Burkert, A., to be submitted to **ApJ**Characterizing the Kinematics of Young Stars in the Radcliffe Wave
- 49. Zucker, C.; Goodman, A. G.; Alves, J.; Shmuel, B.; Koch, E.; Speagle, J. S.; Foley, M.; Finkbeiner, D. P.; Leike, R.; & Enβlin, T., to be submitted to ApJ On the 3D Spatial Topologies of Local Molecular Clouds
- **48.** Speagle, J. S. et al. [18 additional co-authors], to be submitted to ApJ Mapping the Milky Way in 5-D with 170 Million Stars at High Galactic Latitudes
- **47. Speagle, J. S.** et al. [18 additional co-authors], to be submitted to **ApJ**Deriving Stellar Properties, Distances, and Reddenings from Photometry and Astrometry with brutus
- **46.** Eadie, G.; **Speagle, J. S.**; Cisewski-Kehe, J.; Foreman-Mackey, D.; Huppenkothen, D.; Jones, D. E.; Springford, A.; & Tak, H., to be submitted to **Nature Reviews Physics** Recommendations for Bayesian Inference in Astronomy

### **Under Review**

- 45. Emami, R.; Hernquist, L.; Alcock, C.; Genel, S.; Bose, S.; Weinberger, R.; Vogelsberger, M.; Shen, X.; **Speagle, J. S.**; Marinacci, F.; Forbes, J. C.; & Torrey, P.., submitted to **ApJ**Stellar Halo Morphology from TNG50: Twisted and Twisted-Stretched Halos

  arxiv: 2012.12284
- 44. Bonaca, A.; Naidu, R. P.; Conroy, C.; Caldwell, N.; Cargile, P. A.; Han, J.; Johnson, B. D.; Kruijssen, J. M. D.; Myeong, G. C.; **Speagle, J. S.**; Ying, Y.-S.; & Zaritsky, D., submitted to **ApJL**

Orbital Clustering Identifies the Origins of Galactic Stellar Streams arxiv: 2012.09171

- **43.** Johnson, B. D.; Leja, J.; Conroy, C.; & **Speagle**, **J. S.**, submitted to **ApJ**Stellar Population Inference with Prospector

  arxiv: 2012.01426
- 42. Green, G. M.; Tschesche, L.; Rix, H.-W.; Finkbeiner, D. P.; Zucker, C.; Schlafly, E. F.; Rybizki, J.; & **Speagle, J. S.**, submitted to **ApJ**Data-Driven Stellar Models

  arxiv: 2006.16258

#### 2020

- 41. Desprez, G. et al. [171 additional co-authors including **Speagle, J. S.**], **A&A**Euclid Preparation. X. The Euclid Photometric-Redshift Challenge arxiv: 2009.12112
- 40. Carter, C.; Conroy, C.; Zaritsky, D.; Ting, Y.-S.; Bonaca, A.; Naidu, R. P.; Johnson, B. D.; Cargile, P. A.; Caldwell, N.; & **Speagle, J. S.**, **ApJ**Ancient Very Metal-Poor Stars Associated with the Galactic Disk in the H3 Survey
- 39. Zaritsky, D.; Conroy, C.; Naidu, R. P.; Cargile, P. A.; Putman, M.; Besla, G.; Bonaca, A.; Caldwell, N.; Han, J. J.; Johnson, B. D.; **Speagle, J. S.**; & Ting, Y.-S., **ApJL** *Discovery of Magellanic Stellar Debris in the H3 Survey*
- **38. Das, K. K.**; Zucker, C.; **Speagle, J. S.**; Goodman, A.; Schlafly, E. F.; Green, G. M.; Finkbeiner, D. P.; & Alves, J., **MNRAS**Constraining the Distance to the North Polar Spur with Gaia DR2

  arxiv: 2009.01320
- 37. Johnson, B. D.; Conroy, C.; Naidu, R. P.; Bonaca, A.; Zaritsky, D.; Ting, Y.-S.; Cargile, P. A.; Han, J. J.; & Speagle, J. S., ApJ
  A Diffuse Metal-Poor Component of the Sagittarius Stream Revealed by the H3 Survey arxiv: 2007.14408
- Cargile, P. A.; Conroy, C.; Johnson, B. D.; Ting, Y.-S.; Bonaca, A.; Dotter, A.; & Speagle, J. S., ApJ
   MINESweeper: Spectrophotometric Modeling of Stars in the Gaia Era arxiv: 1907.07690
- 35. Cabrera-Ziri, I.; **Speagle, J. S.**; Dalessandro, E.; Usher, C.; Bastian, N. J.; Salaris, M.; Martocchia, S.; Kozhurina-Platais, V.; Niederhofer, F.; Lardo, C.; & Larsen, S. S., **MNRAS**

Searching for Globular Cluster Chemical Anomalies on the Main Sequence of a Young Massive Cluster arxiv: 2004.09636

34. Bonaca, A.; Conroy, C.; Hogg, D. W.; Cargile, P. A.; Caldwell, N.; Naidu, R. P.; Price-Whelan, A. M.; **Speagle, J. S.**; & Johnson, B. D., **ApJL**High Procedution Structure costs of the CD 1 Stellar Stream Localizes: the Dortumber Near the Orl

High-Resolution Spectroscopy of the GD-1 Stellar Stream Localizes the Perturber Near the Orbital Plane of Sagittarius

arxiv: 2001.07215

- 33. Leja, J.; Speagle, J. S.; Johnson, B. D.; Conroy, C.; van Dokkum, P.; & Franx, M., ApJ A New Census of the 0.2 < z < 3.0 Universe, Part I: The Stellar Mass Function arxiv: 1910.04168
- 32. Portillo, S. K. N. & Speagle, J. S.; & Finkbeiner, D. P., AJ

Photometric Biases in Modern Surveys

arxiv: <u>1902.02374</u>

Press: AAS

31. Speagle, J. S., MNRAS

dynesty: A Dynamic Nested Sampling Package for Estimating Bayesian Posteriors and Evidences arxiv: 1904.02180

**30.** Alves, J.; Zucker, C.; Goodman, A. A.; **Speagle, J. S.**; Meingast, S.; Robitaille, T.; Finkbeiner, D. P.; Schlafly, E. F.; & Green, G. M., **Nature**Discovery of a Galactic-scale gas wave in the Solar Neighborhood

arxiv: 2001.08748

Press: Official Website

29. Zucker, C.; Speagle, J. S.; Schlafly, E. F.; Green, G. M.; Finkbeiner, D. P., Goodman, A.; & Alves, J., A&A

A Compendium of Distances to Molecular Clouds in the Star Formation Handbook arxiv: 2001.00591

#### 2019

28. Speagle, J. S., arxiv

A Conceptual Introduction to Markov Chain Monte Carlo Methods

arxiv: 1909.12313

- 27. Green, G. M.; Schlafly, E. F.; Zucker, C.; Speagle, J. S.; & Finkbeiner, D. P., ApJ A 3D Dust Map Based on Gaia, Pan-STARRS 1 and 2MASS arxiv: 1905.02734
- 26. Huang, S.; Leauthaud, A.; Hearin, A.; Behroozi, P.; Bradshaw, C.; Ardila, F.; **Speagle, J. S.**; Tenenti, A.; Bundy, K.; Greene, J.; Sifón, C.; & Bahcall, N., **MNRAS**

Weak Lensing Reveals a Tight Connection Between Dark Matter Halo Mass and the Distribution of Stellar Mass in Massive Galaxies

arxiv: 1811.01139

Press: CfA Science Update

- 25. Speagle, J. S.; Leauthaud, A.; Huang, S.; Bradshaw, C. P.; Ardila, F.; Capak, P. L.; Eisenstein, D. J.; Masters, D. C.; Mandelbaum, R.; More, S.; Simet, M.; & Sifón, C., MNRAS Galaxy-Galaxy Lensing in HSC: Validation Tests and the Impact of Heterogeneous Spectroscopic Training Sets

  arxiv: 1906.05876
- 24. Namikawa, T. et al. [73 additional co-authors including **Speagle, J. S.**], **ApJ**Evidence for the Cross-correlation between Cosmic Microwave Background Polarization Lensing from POLARBEAR and the Cosmic Shear from Subaru Hyper Suprime-Cam arxiv: 1904.02116
- 23. Forbes, J. C.; Krumholz, M. R.; & Speagle, J. S., MNRAS

  Towards a Radially-Resolved Semi-Analytic Model for the Evolution of Disc Galaxies Tuned with Machine Learning

  arxiv: 1810.12919
- 22. Cook, B. A.; Conroy, C.; van Dokkum, P.; & Speagle, J. S., ApJ

  Measuring Star-Formation Histories, Distances, and Metallicities with Pixel Color-Magnitude

  Diagrams I: Model Definition and Mock Tests

  arxiv: 1904.00011
- 21. Safarzadeh, M.; Berger, E.; Leja, J.; & Speagle, J. S., ApJL

  Measuring the Delay Time Distribution of Binary Neutron Stars III. Using the Individual Star

  Formation Histories of Gravitational Wave Event Host Galaxies in the Local Universe

  arxiv: 1905.04310

  Press: AAS NOVA
- 20. Hikage, C. et al. [35 additional co-authors including **Speagle, J. S.**], **PASJ**Cosmology from cosmic shear power spectra with Subaru Hyper Suprime-Cam first-year data arxiv: 1809.09148
- Leja, J.; Johnson, B. D.; Conroy, C.; van Dokkum, P.; Speagle, J. S.; Brammer, G.; Momcheva, I.; Skelton, R.; Whitaker, K. E.; Franx, M; & Nelson, E. J., ApJ An Older, More Quiescent Universe from Panchromatic SED Fitting of the 3D-HST Survey arxiv: 1812.05608
- 18. Zucker, C. & Speagle, J. S.; Schlafly, E. F.; Green, G. M., Finkbeiner, D. P.; Goodman, A. A.; & Alves, J., ApJ
  A Large Catalog of Accurate Distances to Local Molecular Clouds: The Gaia DR2 Edition arxiv: 1902.01425
- 17. Leja, J.; Carnall, A. C.; Johnson, B. D.; Conroy, C.; & Speagle, J. S., ApJ How to Measure Galaxy Star Formation Histories II: Nonparametric Models arxiv: 1811.03637

### 2018

**16.** Zucker, C.; Schlafly E. F.; **Speagle, J. S.**; Green, G. M.; Portillo, S. K. N.; Finkbeiner, D. P.; & Goodman, A. A., **ApJ** 

Mapping Distances Across the Perseus Molecular Cloud Using CO Observations, Stellar Photometry, and Gaia DR2 Parallax Measurements

arxiv: 1803.08931

15. Medezinski, E.; Oguri, M.; Nishizawa, A.; Speagle, J. S.; Miyatake, H.; Umetsu, K.; Leauthaud, A.; Murata, R.; Mandelbaum, R.; Sifón, C.; Strauss, M. A.; Huang, S.; Simet, M.; Okabe, N.; Tanaka, M.; & Yutaka, K., PASJ

Source Selection for Cluster Weak Lensing Measurements in the Hyper Sprime-Cam Survey arxiv: 1706.00427

- 14. Mandelbaum, R. et al. [30 additional co-authors including **Speagle, J. S.**], **PASJ**The first-year shear catalog of the Subaru Hyper Suprime-Cam SSP Survey arxiv: 1706.06745
- Tanaka, M.; Coupon, J.; Hsieh, B.-C.; Mineo, S., Nishizawa, A. J.; Speagle, J.; Furusawa, H.; Miyazaki, S.; & Murayama, H., PASJ

  Photometric Redshifts for the Hyper Suprime-Cam Subaru Strategic Program Data Release 1
  arxiv: 1704.05988
- 12. Aihara, H. et al. [108 additional co-authors including **Speagle, J. S.**], **PASJ**First Data Release of the Hyper Suprime-Cam Subaru Strategic Program

  arxiv: 1702.08449
- 11. Aihara, H. et al. [142 additional co-authors including **Speagle, J. S.**], **PASJ**The Hyper Suprime-Cam SSP Survey: Overview and Survey Design arxiv: 1704.05858
- 10. Oguri, M. et al. [24 additional co-authors including **Speagle, J. S.**], **PASJ**An optically-selected cluster catalog at redshift 0.1<z<1.1 from Hyper Suprime-Cam Subaru Strategic Program \$16A data
  arxiv: 1701.00818

#### 2017

9. Speagle, J. S. & Eisenstein, D. J., MNRAS

Deriving Photometric Redshifts with Fuzzy Archetypes and Self-Organizing Maps II. Implementation arxiv: 1510.08080

8. Speagle, J. S. & Eisenstein, D. J., MNRAS

Deriving Photometric Redshifts with Fuzzy Archetypes and Self-Organizing Maps I. Methodology arxiv: 1510.08073

#### 2016

- 7. Speagle, J. S.; Capak, P. L.; Eisenstein, D. J.; Masters, D. C.; Steinhardt, C. L., MNRAS

  Exploring Photometric Redshifts as an Optimization Problem: An Ensemble MCMC and Simulated

  Annealing-Driven Template-fitting Approach

  arxiv: 1508.02484
- 6. Steinhardt, C. L.; Capak, P. L.; Masters, D. C.; & Speagle, J. S., ApJ

The Impossibly Early Galaxy Problem

arxiv: 1506.01377

#### 2015

Masters, D. C. et al. [19 additional co-authors including Speagle, J. S.], ApJ 5.

> Mapping the Galaxy Color-Redshift Relation: Optimal Photometric Redshift Calibration Strategies for Cosmology Surveys

arxiv: 1509.03318

#### 2014

Steinhardt, C. L. & Speagle, J. S., ApJ 4.

A Uniform History for Galaxy Evolution

arxiv: 1409.2883

Steinhardt, C. L.; Speagle, J. S. et al. [22 additional co-authors], ApJL 3.

> Star Formation at 4 < z < 6 from the Spitzer Large Area Survey with Hyper-Suprime-Cam (SPLASH)

arxiv: 1407.7030

Press: IPL

Speagle, J. S.; Steinhardt, C. L.; Capak, P. L.; & Silverman, J. D., ApJS 2.

A Highly Consistent Framework for the Evolution of the Star-Forming Main Sequence' from z~0-6

arxiv: 1405.2041

#### 2011

Speagle, J. S.; Kaplan, D. L.; & van Kerkwijk, M. H., ApJ 1.

The X-ray Counterpart of the High-B Pulsar J0726-2612

arxiv: 1111.2877